Harriet Randolph Hyatt Mayor Papers
Harriet Randolph Hyatt Mayor Papers
1881-1962
Mayor, Harriet H. (Harriet Hyatt), 1868-1960.
15.5 linear ft.
Correspondence (1892-1960); diaries, genealogical materials, notebooks, photographs, printed material, including articles and clippings, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and sketchbooks. Correspondence includes that of Adelaide Cole Chase, Clara Carter Hyatt Coad, Anna Hyatt and Archer M. Huntington, Audella Hyatt, and Alfred G. Mayor.
149154
Biographical History
Harriet R. Hyatt Mayor was born in Salem, Mass. in 1868, the daughter of Audella Beebe Hyatt and Alpheus Hyatt II, the noted paleontologist. After traveling abroad with her family at an early age she began to show artistic tendencies. She studied art and sculpture in Boston and began a promising career. She encouraged her sister Anna to join her in sculpting. Harriet was married in 1900 to Alfred Goldsborough Mayor and soon began to raise a family. Alfred G. Mayor, son of Alfred M. Mayor, the noted physicist, was an outstanding natural scientist in his own right. He and his wife spent 22 happy years together and had four children, A. Hyatt, Katharine, Brantz, and Barbara.
Mrs. Mayor suffered a slight attack of tuberculosis in 1912 and went abroad with her children. She barely escaped Germany before World War I began. After Dr. Mayor's death in 1922, Mrs. Mayor busied herself with other activities: she traveled in Europe, she also became active in the Daughters of the American Revolution and long served as regent of the Princeton, New Jersey chapter. This association contributed to her interest in genealogy (as well as her mother's similar interest) and she made studies of the Hyatt and Mayor family trees. She lived most of her later years in Princeton, only leaving to live with her sister Anna (Mrs. Archer M. Huntington) during her last year. She died at the Huntington estate in Bethel, Conn., in 1960 at the age of 92.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers of Harriet Hyatt Mayor include correspondence, an address book, artifacts, an autograph collection, bills and receipts, diaries, (1901-04, 1937-38, and undated), genealogy materials, notes and notebooks, photographs, scrapbooks, manuscripts of articles written by Mrs. Mayor, sketchbooks and published material consisting of articles, newspaper clippings, and press releases about Mrs. Mayor and others.
Correspondence, includes incoming, outgoing letters, incoming letters of others, and correspondence by subject. Subject File, contains an address book, artifacts, an autograph book and collection, bills and receipts, catalogues, a cashbook, copies of letters, copyright notices, DAR material, diaries (1901-04, 1937-38, and undated), foreign currency, genealogical materials and correspondence, health reports, legal papers, a medal, notes and notebook, a passport, programs and cards and travel booklets. Photographs, consists of pictures of documents, family and friends and places. Manuscripts, includes articles by Mrs. Mayor and by others, and sketches and sketchbooks. Published Material, contains articles by Mrs. Mayor and others, newspaper clippings about Mrs. Mayor and others, and press releases about others. Duplicates, consists of one folder of articles about Mrs. Mayor's father, Alpheus Hyatt II.
Arrangement of the Collection
The incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author. The outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically. The correspondence of others is all incoming letters to other members of the family arranged alphabetically by recipient and then chronologically. The correspondence by subject is a series of copybooks of letters. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject. These photographs are followed by scrapbooks of photos and also negatives. Manuscripts are organized alphabetically by type and then alphabetically by title. Subject File and Published Material are arranged alphabetically by type.
Related Material
The has numerous collections for the Hyatt-Mayor families. For information on members of the Hyatt, Mayor, Beebe, and Huntington families see for the finding aids of individual family members.
Subject and Genre Headings
Huntington, Anna Hyatt, 1876-1973.; Huntington, Archer M. (Archer Milton), 1870-1955.; Hyatt, Audella Beebe, 1840-1932.; Mayor, Alfred Goldsborough, 1868-1922.; Chase, Adelaide Cole.; Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt.; Mayor, Harriet H. (Harriet Hyatt), 1868-1960 -- Archives.; Hyatt family.; Mayor family.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Upper class -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Women painters -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Genealogies (histories); Notebooks.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - A (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - Chase, Adelaide Cole (Box 1)
    - Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt (Box 1)
    - Cook, Katherine, See Townsend, Katharine Mayor Cook.
    - Dah - Day (Box 1)
    - De - Do (Box 2)
    - E (Box 2)
    - F (Box 2)
    - G, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ha - Hu (Box 2)
    - Hodgdon, Clara Hyatt, See Kent, Clara Hyatt Hodgdon.
    - Huntington, Anna V. Hyatt and Archer M. Huntington (Box 2)
    - Hyatt family, Alpheus Hyatt II, Alpheus Hyatt III, Amy Hyatt, Harriet Hyatt (grandmother) (Box 2)
    - Hyatt, Anna Vaughn, See Huntington, Anna V. Also See Mrs. Huntington's own collection for Mrs. Mayor's replies
    - Hyatt, Audella
      - [General], 1886-1887; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - [General], 1889 (Box 3)
      - [General], 1891-1899; 9 folders (Box 3)
      - [General], 1900, Jul-Dec; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - [General], 1901; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - [General], 1902, Jan-Mar (Box 4)
      - [General], 1902, Apr-Dec; 4 folders (Box 5)
      - [General], 1903-1905; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - [General], 1906-1912; 10 folders (Box 6)
      - [General], 1913-1917; 7 folders (Box 7)
      - [General], 1918-1927; 10 folders (Box 8)
      - [General], 1929 (Box 8)
      - [General], 1932 (Box 8)
      - [General], Undated (Box 8)
      - Unidentified (Box 8)
    - Hyatt, Clara (Clara Carter Hyatt Coad), See Coad, Clara Carter Hyatt.
    - Hyatt, Clara (Clarchen), See Kent, Clara Hyatt Hodgdon.
    - I (Box 9)
    - J (Box 9)
    - K, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Kent, Clara Hyatt Hodgdon (Box 9)
    - L (Box 9)
    - Ma - Me (Box 9)
    - Mayor, Alfred G.
      - [General], 1896-1901; 9 folders (Box 10)
      - [General], 1902-1904; 6 folders (Box 11)
      - [General], 1905-1911, Jun; 12 folders (Box 12)
      - [General], 1911 Jul-1914 Aug; 7 folders (Box 13)
      - [General], 1915-1922; 8 folders (Box 14)
      - [General], Undated; 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Mayor, Alpheus Hyatt (Box 15)
    - Mayor family, Alfred H., Brantz (2), Edwin, Ella, Harriet, Katharine, (2) Lewis, Martha, Mary, Susan, Virginia (Box 15)
    - Mayor, Barbara, See Money, Barbara Mayor.
    - Mayor, Katharine, See Townsend, Katharine Mayor Cook.
    - Mayor, Maria S.
      - [General], 1897-1900; 1908,; 1911,; 1918,; 1920 (Box 15)
      - [General], 1922-1923; 1926-1928 (Box 15)
      - [General], 1930-1934; undated (Box 15)
    - Mo - Mu (Box 15)
    - Money, Barbara (Box 15)
    - N (Box 15)
    - O (Box 15)
    - P (Box 16)
    - Paton, F. Margaret & Stewart (Box 16)
    - R (Box 16)
    - S (Box 16)
    - T (Box 16)
    - U (Box 16)
    - V (Box 16)
    - Wal - Wat (Box 16)
    - We - Wr (Box 17)
    - Y (Box 17)
    - Unidentifiable, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - [General], 1895-1958 (Box 17)
    - [General], Undated (Box 17)
  - Correspondence of others, incoming
    - Hyatt, Alpheus III, 1889; 1892,; undated; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Mayor, Brantz, 1921; undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Money, Barbara Mayor, 1910-1934; undated; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Townsend, Katharine Mayor Cook, 1907; 1910,; 1915-1922,; undated; 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Subject:
    - Copybook of letters, 3 (Box 18)
- Subject files
  - Address book (Box 19)
  - Articles about Alpheus Hyatt (Box 19)
  - Artifacts (Box 19)
  - Artifacts (Box 20)
  - Autograph book (Box 20)
  - Autograph collection (Box 20)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 20)
  - Catalogues (Box 20)
  - Cash Book, Morven Society of Princeton, N.J. (Box 20)
  - Copies of letters (Box 20)
  - Copyright notices, 1893; 1895-1897,; 1903; 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution (Box 20)
  - Diary, 1901-1904 (Box 20)
  - Diary, 1937-1938 (Box 21)
  - Diaries, 2 (Box 21)
  - Foreign currency (Box 21)
  - Genealogy correspondence, 3 folders (Box 21)
    For more of Mrs. Mayor's genealogical correspondence, see the Related Material above.
  - Health reports on T.B. (Box 22)
  - Legal papers (Box 22)
  - Mayor, Alfred B., obituary (Box 22)
  - Medal (Box 22)
  - Notes, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Notebook from art classes (Box 22)
  - Notebook on "Clermont" (Box 22)
  - Passport (Box 22)
  - Poetry (Box 22)
  - Programs and cards (Box 22)
  - Travel Booklets (Box 22)
- Photographs
  - Documents and pictures (Box 23)
  - "Edmund, the Lion, and the Alphabet" (Box 23)
  - Family and friends, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Family and friends, 5 folders (Box 24)
  - Places, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Scrapbook, 1 (Box 25)
  - Scrapbook, 4 (Box 26)
  - Scrapbook, 1 (Box 27)
  - Works by Anna Hyatt Huntington (Box 27)
  - Works by Harriet Hyatt Mayor (Box 27)
  - Negatives, 4 folders (Box 28)
  - Negatives, glass (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous oversize, 2 items (Oversize 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles
    - "An Evening among the Cannibal Islands" (Box 29)
    - "My Grandmother Hyatt" (Box 29)
    - "In ye Palace by the Sea" (Box 29)
    - "My Own Town" (Box 29)
    - "The Passing of Bridget" (Box 29)
    - Untitled (Box 29)
    - "Unveiling of Memorial Tablet and Bas Relief of Alpheus Hyatt", author unknown (Box 29)
    - "A Woman's Duty" (Box 29)
  - Articles by others
    - Unidentified (Box 29)
  - Sketches
    - Early sketches by Harriet Hyatt Mayor (Box 29)
    - Sketches (Box 29)
    - Sketchbook, 2 (Box 29)
    - Sketchbook, 2 (Box 30)
    - Sketches, unidentified (Box 30)
- Published material
  - Articles by Harriet Hyatt Mayor (Box 31)
  - Articles by others (Box 31)
  - "Babson's Washington Forecast" (Box 31)
  - Newspaper clippings about Harriet Hyatt Mayor (Box 31)
  - Newspaper clippings about others (Box 31)
  - Press releases about others (Box 31)
- Duplicates
  - Articles about Alpheus Hyatt, 1 folder (Box 31)